Guide to the Stanford University, Asian American Activities Center, Records SC0487
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Asian American Activities Center, records
circa 1970-2017
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University. Asian American Activities Center
SC0487
42.75 Linear Feet
The collection includes correspondence, memoranda, minutes, proposals, course materials, financial records, newspaper clippings, subject files, flyers, photos, publications and other records pertaining to the history and recent activities of Stanford Asian American students, staff, faculty and alumni. Included are materials pertaining to Asian American Studies, the Asian American Activities Center and its affiliated student organizations as well as historic materials documenting early student efforts to establish these organizations and programs. These materials would be useful to those seeking information about the history of the Stanford Asian American community/Asian American student organizations/or significant events that helped to establish and shape the community.
Custodial History
The materials were gathered and organized by the Asian American Activities Center and transferred to the Archives in 1995, 1997, 2003, 2010, 2015, and 2016.
Information about Access
The collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use.
Historical Note:
Early History Asian and Asian American students have been a part of Stanford history beginning with the inaugural class in 1891. The Japanese Students Association and the Chinese Students Association were founded in the early 1900s as the first Asian and Asian American voluntary student organizations. In 1913, the first professor of Asian decent, Yamato Ichihashi, was hired in the history department. Racial tensions resulted in the establishment of the Japanese Clubhouse (1916) and the Chinese Clubhouse (1919) as safe residences for students of Asian descent.
In 1942, 24 students of Japanese descent and Professor Ichihashi and his wife were removed from campus and sent to internment camps as a result of Executive Order 9066.
1960's and 1970's During the period of the Civil Rights Movement, Asian American students began to organize and advocate for their needs. The Asian American Student Alliance, which later bacame the Stanford Students Coordinating Committee and now the Asian American Students' Association, formed in 1969. That same year, inspired by Black Student Union protests following the assassination of Martin Luther King, Jr, Asian American students started a petition for Asian American Studies.
An Asian American theme dorm, Junipero which became Okada House, was established in 1971, followed by the People's Teahouse, which became the Okada Teahouse and Teahouse. In 1975, the Asian American New Student Orientation Committee was established to introduce new students to the community. The Asian American Sourcebook and Big Brother/Big Sibling Program (which became Big Sib/Little Sib) followed as well as the Asian American Theater Project founded by then student David Henry Hwang.
In 1977, the Asian American Activities Center is established in the Old Fire Truck House and staffed by volunteer student interns (the precursor to the Center was the Asian American Resource Center that was housed in Junipero in the early 1970's).
1980's In 1982, four Stanford students were featured on the cover of Newsweek with a headline, "Asian-Americans: The Drive to Excel," feeding misperceptions of Asian Americans as the "model minority."
In 1986, an undergraduate student, Jeffrey Au, raised questions about Asian American admissions which prompted a study by the Academic Senate Committee which found "unconscious bias" affected admissions rates for Asian Americans. Immediately following rates of admission increased dramatically.
In 1987, students form the Rainbow Agenda issue demands, including the institutionalization of the Center. Julian Low is hired as a half-time Director and Elsa Tsutaoka is the office manager.
With the growth of the Asian American student population, the first wave of diverse Asian American student organizations were founded from 1988-89. Following the student Take Over of the President's Office, the Asian American Activities Center was instutionalized and the first full time director, Rick Yuen, was hired. Also as a result of the Take Over, in 1990, two Asian American Studies faculty were hired, Gordon Chang and David Palumbo-Liu, and the first Asian American Studies courses were offered the following year.
Organizations founded during this period include: Chinese Folk Dance, Stanford University Nikei (now Japanese Student Union), Stanford Vietnamese Association (now Stanford Vietnamese Students Association), Stanford Wushu, Hong Kong Student Association, Korean Students Association (which became Korean American Students Association before reverting back to Korean Students Association), Stanford "K" Club of India (now Sanskriti), the Thai-American Intercultural Society,the Undergraduate Chinese American Association, the Pilipino American Student Union (although there was a Filipino Student Union in the early 1070's), the Taiwanese American Students Association (now Taiwanese Cultural Society), Asian American Women's Group (which became Stanford Asian Women), the Asian Law Students Association (now the Asian Pacific Islander Law Students Association), Asian American Medical Students (now Asian Pacific American Medical Students Association).
The 1990's The growth in Asian American student organizations continue with the establishment of: Stanford Taiko, Lambda Phi Epsilon, alpha Kappa Delta Phi, Project AIYME, Stanford Hwimori, Newtype Anime Club, Singaporeans at Stanford, Indonesian Club at Stanford.
In 1994 Chicana students went on a hunger strike to demand the reinstatement of a senior Chicana adminisrator, the establishment of an ethnic studies program and a grape boycott. Asian American students disrupt a faculty senate meeting demanding Asian American Studies. The Center for Comparative Studies in Race and Ethnicity is esstablished, followed by the creation of the Asian American Studies program in 1997.
In 1995 the Mibority Alumni Hall of Fame is established by the ethnic community centers to recognize the contributions of outstanding alumni of color.
In 1996 the Queer and Asian student organization was founded to provide a safe space for students to explore issues concerning the Asian American and LGBT identities.
2000 to Present As the Asian American student population became more diverse, new student organizations were established including: the Multiracial Identified Community at Stanford (there was a Half Asian Peoples Association in the late 1980's), Malaysians at Stanford, Pakistanis at Stanford, Muslim Student Awareness Network, Bhangra, Hindi Film Dance, Stanford Asian American Activist Committee, Noopor, Kayumanggi, Sigma Psi Zeta.
The Center offers a new Speaker Series focused on underrepresented Filipino, Southeast Asian and South Asian ethnicities. In 2004 students protest at the Dean of Admissions Office to demand an increase in Filipino and Southeast Asian student outreach and admissions.
In 2006 the Center convened a Task Force to study mental health concerns for Asian American students. A survey was conducted in 2007 and results led to the creation of the After Dark (now iLive) program focusing on Asian American mental health and well-being issues.
In 2007 the Hmong Student Union and Stanford Khmer Association were established.
Chronology
1763 Settlement of Filipino Americans First recorded settlement of Filipinio Americans. They escaped imprisonment aboard Spanish galleons in New Orleans and fled to the bayous.
1790 Naturalization Act The Natualization Act made it law that only "free white persons" could become US citizens.
1790 US-India slave trade First recorded arrival of an Asian Indian in the U.S. They were slaves who were part of the U.S. - India slave trade.
1848 Gold Rush Begins Gold is discovered at Sutter's Mill and word spreads of "Gold Mountain" encouraging many Chinese to emigrate to the US through San Francisco, settling in Sacramento.
1865 Chinese Railroad laborers Central Pacific Railraod Co. recruits Chinese workers for the first transcontinental railroad. 9,000 of the 10,000 laborers for the project were Chinese.
1882 Chinese Exclusion Act Suspends immigration of Chinese laborers for 10 years and excludes Chinese from citizenship by naturalization and halts Chinese immigration for 60 years.
1891 Representation in Stanford's Pioneer Class The first annual Stanford register lists 7 students with Asian surnames out of the 555 students in the Pioneer Class.
1898 Annexation of Hawai'i U.S. annexes Hawaii after 160 American armed marines land in Honolulu. Hawai'I later becomes the state with the highest concentration of Asian Americans and Pacific Islanders.
1902 Japanese Students Association Founded With an enrollment of 30 students, the Japanese Students Association formed to build a supportive community for Japanese nationals and US born students of Japanese decent.
1906 The Great San Francisco Earthquake A magnitue 7.8 earthquake hits San Francisco sparking fires that destroy over 80% of the city. The loss of government records allows for the entry of "paper sons" from China who were allowed to enter based on forged birth certificates claiming their fathers resided in the US.
1910 Angel Island Established as a detention center for Asian non-laboring classes desiring entry into the U.S. Thousands of immigrants from China endure weeks and even years of interrogation by US immigration officers. The center serves as the "Ellis Island of the West" until 1940. Chinese Students Association Founded Chinese students both American born and from China gathered together to support each other at Stanford.
1913 First Professor of Asian Decent Yamato Ichihashi began teaching in the History department specializing in Japanese history, international relations, and the Japanese American experience. By the 1920s, he was appointed Associate Professor and is believed to be the first person of Asian decent to have held an endowed chair position at an American university.
1916 Tensions in Campus Housing A student of Chinese decent was physically thrown out of the residences at Encina Hall by white male students. This action prompted the Chinese and Japanese communities at Stanford to raise funds to establish residences on campus for their students.
1916 Establishment of Japanese Clubhouse Japanese Students establish the Japanese Clubhouse on Santa Ynez Street. The clubhouse provided a safe home for students of Japanese ancestry on campus until the start of WWII.
1919 Establishment of the Chinese Clubhouse Chinese community establishes the Stanford Chinese Clubhouse located on Salvatierra where the law school currently stands. Much like a present day row house, the residence included housing for current students as well as a kitchen and lounge for community gatherings.
1929 Anti-Filipino Violence As the Filipino population increases. Anti-Filipino riots and murders occur up and down the West Coast.
1935 Filipino Repatriation Act Offers to pay the way back to the Philippines for Filipinos choosing to go. 2000 Filipinos leave.
1942 Executive Order 9066: Japanese American Internment Puts 120,000 Japanese (primarily U.S. citizens) in 10 concentration camps. Students & Faculty of Japanese Decent Sent to Internment Camps President Franklin Roosevelt signed Executive Order 9066 authorizing the wartime internment of 120,000 U.S. citizens and residents of Japanese ancestry. At the time 24 students with Japanese surnames were enrolled at Stanford and were forced to leave along with Professor Yamato Ichihashi and wife Kei who remained in the camps until the end of the war.
1944 Korematsu vs. US Supreme court rules that Executive Order 9066 ) constitutional.
1965 National Origins Act Raises Asian immigration to 20,000 per year for Asian countries, the same as European countries. The new act favors educated middle class immigrants therby changing the class dynamics of the Asian American community.
1965 - 1973 Vietnam War US involvement in the Vietnam War. The draft began for all males born between 1944-1950. Nationwide college students protested the war following the fatal shootings at Kent State in 1970. Stanford Campus Vietnam Protests Students and faculty protest Stanford's policy on Selective Service examinations and classified research including Stanford Research Institute's work on chemical weapons. By 1970 the Board of Trustees voted to sever ties with SRI.
1967 Coining of the term "Asian American" Yuji Ichioka, a UCLA scholar, coined the term to bring diverse Asian groups together as he formed the first pan-Asian American political group - the Asian American Political Alliance. Previously people of Asian decent were referred to as Asiatic or Oriental.
1969 Asian American Student Alliance (later known as the Asian American Students' Association) Formed AASA was formed to help Asian Americans meet and understand more about each other though social and cultural programs and to bring attention to Asian American student needs on campus. | People's Disco; National coalition for redress and reparations for Japanese Americans incarcerated during WWII; students seek minority status for Asians at Stanford (1981)
1969 The fight for Asian American Studies at Stanford Begins Following the assassination of Martin Luther King, Jr., students from the Black Student Union interrupted an address by Provost Richard Lyman and presented a set of demands which led to the establishment of the program in African and Afro-American Studies. Inspired by this action, Asian American students start a petition for Asian American Studies to develop new knowledge and understanding of the Asian community and experience and above all, to cultivate self-awareness among the Asian American student body.
1971 Asian American Theme Dorm Established Junipero House founded as the Asian American Theme Dorm to foster Asian American ethnic and cultural understanding within a residential setting. Anthropology Professor Harumi Befu is the first Resident fellow. An Asian American Resource center was housed in Junipero until space became available in the Firetruck house in 1977.
1971 The first Asian American Studies Course Gordon Chang, a then-graduate student in History, teaches the first Asian American Studies course offered under the student led Stanford Workshops on Political and Social Issues (SWOPSI).
1974 The People's Teahouse Students establish a non-profit student-run organization that donates funds to worth-while Asian American related projects and groups on campus and in the surrounding community.
1975 The Fall of Saigon The official end of the Vietnam War signaled the arrival of large numbers of Vietnamese refugees in the US. Over 700,000 refugees from Southeast Asia settled in the US during a ten year span. Asian American New Student Orientation Committee Established Established by students to welcome incoming Asian American students and to introduce them to the activities, organizations, and aspirations of the Asian American community at Stanford. Started the Asian American Sourcebook and Big Brother / Big Sibling Program.
1977 I-Hotel Evictions Eviction of elderly Filipino and Chinese tenants from International Hotel in San Francisco Asian American Activities Center Established Asian American Activities Center is located at the Old Fire Truck House and staffed entirely by volunteer student interns.
1978 Asian American Theater Project Established To help shape a more realistic image of Asian Americans in theater and to present relevant Asian American works.
1981 Okada House Founded The Asian American Theme dorm moved from Junipero House to Madera in Wilbur Hall and was renamed Okada House in honor of John Okada (1924-1971), pioneer Asian American artist and author of the novel No-No Boy. The dorm is home to 96 students 40% Asian American.
1982 Vincent Chin and National Asian American Identity Chinese American Vincent Chin was murdered in Detroit at the height of layoffs in the US auto industry due to increasing Japanese imports. Asian American groups around the country rallied to classify the murder as a hate crime and to build coaltions to push for Federal prosecution. This fuels a national Asian American movement. Model Minority Newsweek Cover The magazine Newsweek On Campus features 4 Stanford students posing in the Quad under the headline "Asian-Americans: The Drive to Excel" feeding misperceptions of Asian Americans as the "Model Minority"
1986 Admissions Policy Questioned Prompted by the questions raised to Dean of Admissions Jean Fetter by Stanford Junior Jeffrey Au, the Academic Senate Committee conducts a study of Asian American admissions. The committee finds that "unconscious bias" caused the discrepancy in admissions rates and immediately following the report, admissions rates for Asian American students increased to 89 percent of the white admission rate.
1987 Rainbow Agenda & Institutionalizing the Community Centers Students form the Rainbow Agenda (including AASA, MEChA, SAIO, BSU) propose a set of demands including the institutionalization of the Asian American Activities Center and the hiring of a full time Director/Dean; Julian Low becomes the first half time Director of the new department and Elsa Tsutaoka is the office manager.
1987-1988 Western Culture Curriculum Debate Students rallied to change the required first year Western Cultures course that included predominantly works of European-Western authors advocating instead for a curriculum that included ethnic minority and women authors. Reverend Jesse Jackson led a march down Palm Drive with over 200 students chanting "Hey hey, ho ho, Western Civ has got to go," and the curriculum debate drew national media attention. In 1989 Western Cultures was replaced by a new course for freshmen, Cultures, Ideas, & Values (CIV), that included works on race, class, and gender.
1988 Students of Color Coalition The Students of Color Coalition leads a rally against racism from White Plaza to the Quad to present a platform for multicultural education at Stanford.
1988 - 1989 Founding of Many API Student Organizations As the Asian American student population grows, new student organizations representing the breath of diversity within the community flourish. Chinese Folk Dance, Stanford University Nikkei, Stanford Vietnamese Association, Stanford Wushu, Hong Kong Student Association, Korean Students Association, Pilipino American Students Association, Stanford "K"lub of India (Sanskriti), the Thai-American Intercultural Society, and the Undergraduate Chinese American Association were all founded during this time.
1989 University Committee on Minority Issues Formed in response to the demands of the student led Rainbow Agenda, the President and Provost form the University Committee on Minority Issues. The UCMI report outlines recommendations for: diversifying curriculum; minority faculty recruitment, retention & promotion; student admissions and financial aid; student life; and staff recruitment, retention & promotion.
1989 Takeover of the President's Office Students take over President Donald Kennedy's Office with a list of 120 demands including Asian American Studies at Stanford, chanting… "JUST ONE ASIAN AMERICAN HISTORY PROFESSOR". Kennedy releases a statement to the press saying "We confirm that many minority issues and concerns are not the special pleadings of interest groups but are Stanford issues--ones that should engage all of us" and states goal to hire 30 minority faculty in the following decade.
1989 Asian American Activities Center Institutionalized with First Full Time Director The Asian American Activities center is institutionalized through funding from the Dean of Student Affairs which enables the hiring of the first full time director Rick Yuen.
1990 Report on Building Multicultural University Community As a follow up to the UCMI report, the Annual Review Panel released an assessment with recommendations to: institutionalize multiculturalism as a university value; incorporate multicultural goals in internal planning processes; and increase institutional accountability through an Internal University Minority Audit Group composed of faculty, staff, senior administrators and students.
1990 Asian American Studies Courses offered Professors Gordon Chang and David Palumbo-Liu are the first to be appointed as tenure-track Asian American Studies scholars. The following year, Asian American Studies scholars offer a core curriculum consisting of five Asian American Studies courses, as a result of collaborative efforts of Profs. Chang, Palumbo-Liu, Sylvia Yanagisako, and Bill Hing.
1991-1993 More API Student Groups Founded Asian American student groups continue to grow in number, adding performing arts and greek organizations including Stanford Taiko, Lambda Phi Epsilon, alpha Kappa Delta Phi, Project AYIME, Stanford Hwimori, Newtype Anime club, Singaporeans at Stanford, Indonesian Club at Stanford, and the Asian American Sib Program.
1991 Asian American Activities Center Professional Staff Increases to Two Full Time Positions Cindy Ng is hired as the second full time professional staff member at the Asian American Activities Center starting as a Program Coordinator.
1992 Los Angeles Riots After the acquittal of the white LAPD officers who were filmed beating black motorist Rodney King, one of the biggest riots begins in LA. For days, massive violence, destruction, and looting erupts throughout the city. Over 2000 Korean-owned business are destroyed. Aftermath of the LA Riots Jesse Jackson speaks at Memorial Auditorium on the issue of Anti-Asian violence following the Los Angeles Riots.
1993 Support for Ethnic Community Centers In response to potential budget cuts to the ethnic community centers, students hold a speak out in White Plaza, titled “Bridging the Gap Between Rhetoric and Reality
1993 Asian American Interactive Mentoring Program Established Responding to the UCMI report findings, the Asian American Activities Center establishes the first mentoring program for undergraduate students at Stanford focused on support and retention with a lens of cultural understanding. Faculty, staff, and alumni sign up to mentor sophomore students through the program.
1993 -1994 Ethnic Center Staff Equity Assistant Directors in the ethnic community centers were reclassified and received pay increases following an investigation into equity to bring them on par with the Assistant Directors in the Office of Student Activities.
1994 Opportunities and Challenges In response to the request for budget cut scenarios, the ethnic community centers submit a report making a case for further investment instead of cuts, highlighting the increased demand for services from the community centers given the diverse student body.
1994 Concerned Students for Asian American Studies Concerned Students for Asian American Studies members disrupt a Faculty Senate meeting, demanding consideration for an Asian American Studies Program. It is the first time that a Faculty Senate meeting is prematurely adjourned. The following year an Asian American Studies Curriculum Committee is formed and charged with developing a curriculum for an Asian American Studies major and minor.
1994 Four Chicano students go on hunger strike Hunger strikers demand reinstatement of a senior Chicana administrator, the establishment of a Chicano Studies program and a grape boycott on campus. Students from AASA, BSU and SAIO join in support of the strikers.